Inventory of the Howard A. Reed papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Howard A. Reed papers
1909-2000
89010
Reed, Howard A. (Howard Alexander), 1920-
118 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (48 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, notes, curricular material, conference papers and proceedings, and printed matter, relating to the promotion of international education in the United States; Middle Eastern area studies, and especially Turkish studies, in the United States; and activities of the American Friends Service Committee and other organizations in promoting education for peace and international exchange programs for students.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989, with increments added in 1993 and 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1920 February 26 Born, Izmir, Turkey
1942 BA in Modern European History and Languages, Yale University
1949 MA, Princeton University
1950-1952 History department staff, Yale University
1951 PhD in History of the Near East and Oriental Studies, Princeton University
1955-1957 Program specialist in International Training and Research, Ford Foundation (New York City and Beirut)
1957-1958 Lecturer and researcher on Islam and the Middle East, Pendle Hill
1958-1960 National director, American Friends Service Committee, Colleges and Projects Programs in U.S. and abroad
1958-1973 Board member, Pendle Hill
1960-1964 Associate director, The Danforth Foundation
1967-1971 Director of International and Intercultural Studies, University of Connecticut at Storrs
1967-1989 Professor of History (Middle Eastern, Islamic and Ottoman), University of Connecticut at Storrs
1969 Board member, American Research Institute, Turkey
1978 Program director, University of Connecticut, Storrs, International Studies Program
1981 January-May Visiting scholar, Hoover Institution, researching modern Turkey
Circa 1989 Professor emeritus, University of Connecticut at Storrs
1991-1995 Special consultant to four successive ministers of National Education of Turkey
Source: "Howard Alexander Reed." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2002
Scope and Content of Collection
The Howard A. Reed papers document the development of international education programs, in particular Middle East and Turkish studies, at the University of Connecticut at Storrs and across the United States. In addition the papers reflect Reed's work with the American Friends Service Committee in promoting the research of peace through international exchange programs for students, as well as his work as a consultant to ministers of National Education in Turkey. The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, notes, curricular material, conference papers and proceedings, meeting minutes, photographs, printed matter, and sound recordings.
The University of Connecticut file contains materials relating to the administrative and educational activities of the History Department of the University of Connecticut at Storrs, where Howard Reed was a professor of Islamic, Middle East, and Ottoman history and director of the Institute of International and Intercultural Studies. In 1978 Reed was awarded a $57,000 three-year federal grant to coordinate a statewide international studies program for undergraduates. As director of the Undergraduate International Studies Program (UISP) Reed was responsible for coordinating a mobile outreach program to community colleges, structuring the curriculum, inviting guest speakers and lecturers, and promoting exchange programs with universities in other countries. The materials relating to this program can be found in the University of Connecticut file as well as the Subject file and are in the form of grant applications, financial records, flyers, promotional materials, correspondence with participating state colleges and universities, newspaper clippings, and other printed matter.
The Subject file covers a wide variety of topics related to education and the Middle East. Brochures, correspondence, newsletters, and other materials by Friends World College, a college based on Quaker principles and the promotion of peace and international studies, are found in this series.
Reed co-founded the Middle East Studies Association and Turkish Studies Association in North America. The Middle East Studies Association file includes correspondence about the first MESA conference in 1967 and conference materials from subsequent meetings.
Materials relating to Turkish Studies are in the collection in the form of Turkish newspapers, journals, conference papers and proceedings, and course materials. Much of Reed's writings and research on Turkey, its history and education system, can be found in this series as well as in the National Education of Turkey consultant file, which includes mostly printed materials collected during Reed's time as a consultant to the Turkish minister of national education.
As the grandson of International College founder, Alexander MacLachlan, and son of one of its early presidents Cass Arthur Reed, Reed's interest in international education was shaped by International College. The papers include research material about the International College of Izmir, which was later relocated to Beirut, Lebanon. Highlights from these materials include copies of minutes from meetings of Board of Trustees from the early years of the college and photographs of students from 1914 to 1920.
Index to Major Groups
Papers are arranged in the order in which they were received. Although the collection is not physically arranged, most materials fall into the following groups.
1-13, 20-21, 23, 28-38, 48-62, 64, 68-78, 85-86, 89-91 University of Connecticut file, 1965-1988. Includes memoranda, correspondence, reports, printed matter, conference materials, curricular material, photographs, and sound recordings relating mainly to the development of international studies (primarily Middle East studies) at the University of Connecticut at Storrs and subsequently other colleges and universities in the United States.
14-20, 24-27, 39-46, 62-64, 70, 84, 87, 91-92, 94, 95 Subject file, 1959-1989. Includes correspondence, memoranda, conference materials, reports, sound recordings, newsletters, journals, brochures, and other printed matter. Original folder titles retained in the description of collection materials
66, 82-83, 111-112, 116 Middle East Studies Association file, 1966-1974, 1994. Includes conference materials, correspondence, and by-laws.
78-81, 86, 88, 93 Turkish Studies file, 1920-1986 Includes correspondence, curricular material, conference materials, meeting minutes, reports, and printed matter relating to Turkish Studies programs and conferences in the United States and to education in Turkey.
99-113 National Education of Turkey consultant file, 1983-1999. Includes research materials in the form of magazines, journals, reports, articles, correspondence, and brochures relating to the development of higher education in Turkey and to the Turkish economy.
113-114, 117-119 International College file, 1909-1999. Includes research materials for Reed's study on the history of International College in Izmir and Beirut in the form of brochures, yearbooks, correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, photographs, postcards, and negatives.
67, 70, 80, 84-85, 97-98, 114 Printed matter, 1967-2000. Includes newspapers, journals, monographs, clippings, and newsletters.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
American Friends Service Committee.; Peace--Study and teaching.; International education.; Education--United States.; Middle East--Study and teaching.; Turkey--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- University of Connecticut file (Folder 1-13)
  - Undergraduate International Studies Program (Folder 1-4)
    - Time and effort and budget files, 1978-1981 (Folder 1)
    - Time and effort and budget files, 1978-1980 (Folder 2: 1-19)
    - Grade distribution, 1980 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Faculty meeting, 1980 May (Folder 2: 21)
      Includes some materials from 1979 faculty meetings
    - Speakers and program publicity, 1980-1981 (Folder 2: 22-23)
    - Courses--Administrative approval, 1980-1981 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Final course reports, 1979-1980 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Honors and interdisciplinary studies, 1981 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Program publicity, 1980-1981 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Courses and course materials (Folder 3-4)
      - Human Values, 1980-1981 (Folder 3: 3-4)
      - Course evaluations, 1980-1981 (Folder 3: 5)
      - An Introduction to Global Education, 1980 Spring (Folder 3: 6)
      - World Studies, Education for Modernization in the Third World, 1980 Spring (Folder 3: 7)
      - Faculty schedule, 1980 Spring (Folder 3: 8)
      - INTL 100-Social Consequences of Engineering, 1981 Spring (Folder 3: 9-11)
      - Global Education: Issues and answers, 1981 Spring (Folder 3: 12)
      - International Economics and Politics, 1981 Spring (Folder 4: 1)
      - Modules, 1980 (Folder 4: 2)
      - ART 278-The Arts of Spain and Mexico: Islamic Heritage to Independence, 1980 (Folder 4: 3)
      - Harvesting the World-Humanities Dependence on the Political Economy and Science of Strategic Plants, 1980 (Folder 4: 4)
      - Africa and Latin America, 1980 (Folder 4: 5)
      - Multi-cultural studies, 1980 (Folder 4: 6)
      - History 101-07, 1982 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Conference materials (Folder 4-5)
    - Maps and reimbursement information, 1978 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Undergraduate International Studies Program Conference, 1978 November 3 (Folder 4: 9-18)
    - World Studies and Human Resource Development in Public Higher Education in Connecticut, 1978 September 22 (Folder 4: 19-20)
      Includes transcripts of speeches made by Maurice Harari, William McNeil, and Saul Mendlovitz
    - World Studies and Human Resource Development in Public Higher Education in Connecticut, 1978 September 22 (Contd.) (Folder 5: 1-8)
    - Mailing labels, undated (Folder 5: 9-10)
    - Poster list, undated (Folder 5: 11)
  - Middle East Studies Council (Folder 5-6)
    - General (Folder 5: 12)
    - Kazemzadeh, Firuz, 1980 (Folder 5: 13)
      Includes photograph
    - Naby, Eden, 1980 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Sigliani, Nicholas, 1980 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Lecturers, 1979 Fall (Folder 6: 1)
  - International Studies program background materials, 1978-1980 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Friends World College, 1979 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Values in politics, 1967-1970 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Palestine Human Rights Campaign, 1977-1980 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Institute of International and Intercultural Studies planning documents, 1970 (Folder 6: 6)
  - International Studies Program publicity file, 1979 (Folder 6: 7)
  - International Studies Program publicity file, 1976 (Folder 7: 1-5)
  - International Fair, 1980 April 20 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Informational file on international studies programs, 1980 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Phone numbers and addresses, 1976 (Folder 7: 8-9)
  - Research Foundation reports, 1979 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Memoranda list, undated (Folder 7: 11)
  - Book list, undated (Folder 7: 12)
  - Action sheet, undated (Folder 7: 13)
  - Memoranda sent and received, 1979-1980 (Folder 8)
  - Memoranda sent and received, 1980-1981 (Folder 9: 1-4)
  - Informational file, 1979 Fall (Folder 9: 5-6)
  - United States Senate bills and legislation relating to higher education, 1978-1979 (Folder 9: 7-10)
  - "Strength Through Wisdom: A Critique of U.S. Capability. A Report to the President from the President's Commission on Foreign Language and International Studies,", 1979 November (Folder 9: 11)
  - International and Middle East Studies Program publicity files, 1978-1979 (Folder 10: 1-2)
  - Committees (Folder 10)
    - Advisory Committee, 1978 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Curriculum committee, 1978-1979 (Folder 10: 4-5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1978 (Folder 10: 6-7)
    Mostly to and from John Manning and Richard Long
  - Course catalog materials, 1979-1982 (Folder 10: 8-12)
  - Curriculum reform memoranda and meeting minutes, 1980 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Miscellaneous office files, 1979 (Folder 10: 14-15)
  - Letter regarding critical languages at the University of Connecticut at Storrs, 1980-1981 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Conference materials (Folder 11-13)
    - Conference on Japan, 1979 November (Folder 11: 2-10)
      Includes 2 compact cassette tapes of lectures by Professors Robert Lentner and Hideo Sato from Yale University
    - Opening Doors: Contemporary Japan, Asia Society, 1979 January (Folder 11: 11)
    - "China Today" conference materials, 1980 (Folder 12: 1-2)
    - Energy Conference, 1980 (Folder 12: 13)
      Includes 4 compact cassette tapes
    - Energy Conference, 1980 (Folder 13: 1)
      Includes 7 compact cassette tapes
- United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare memoranda and printed matter relating to international and foreign language studies, 1968 (Folder 13: 2-4)
- United States House of Representatives hearings on energy and education, pamphlets, 1979-1980 (Folder 13: 5)
- Subject file (Folder 14-19)
  - University of Connecticut (Folder 14-15)
    - General, 1967-1969 (Folder 14: 1)
    - African American Cultural Center, 1972 (Folder 14: 2)
    - Alumni awards, 1974 (Folder 14: 3)
    - Branches, 1972 (Folder 14: 4)
    - College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1971-1973 (Folder 14: 5)
    - Connecticut Research Commission, 1970 (Folder 14: 6)
    - Council on Human Rights and Opportunities, 1968 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Education School, 1969 (Folder 14: 8)
    - Graduate faculty meeting materials, 1971-1972 (Folder 14: 9)
    - Graduate School, 1969 (Folder 14: 10)
    - History Department newsletter, 1971 (Folder 14: 11)
    - List of foreign students, 1969 (Folder 14: 12)
    - Newsletter, 1971 (Folder 14: 13)
    - Provost, 1972 (Folder 14: 14)
    - Student affairs, 1972 (Folder 14: 15)
    - University senate, 1968-1969 (Folder 14: 16)
    - Unites States Office of Education (USOE)Faculty team trip to Turkey, 1969-1970 (Folder 14: 17)
    - USOE report research materials, 1967 (Folder 14: 18)
    - Urban business interim program, undated (Folder 14: 19)
    - U.S. Publish Health Service (USPHS), 1971 (Folder 14: 20)
    - War/Peace courses syllabus, undated (Folder 14: 21)
    - Research Foundation, 1959-1960 (Folder 15: 1)
  - Urban affairs, 1969 (Folder 15: 2)
  - Utah, University of, 1971 (Folder 15: 3)
  - Values, 1972 (Folder 15: 4)
  - Verde Valley School, 1970 (Folder 15: 5)
  - Vermont, University of, 1963-1965 (Folder 15: 6)
  - Viewpoints, published by American Friends of the Middle East, 1966 (Folder 15: 7)
  - Virginia University Center, undated (Folder 15: 8)
  - Vitas, undated (Folder 15: 9-10)
  - Visitors, 1965 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Volkmar, John, undated (Folder 15: 12)
  - Volunteer service, 1965 (Folder 15: 13)
  - Vryonis, Speros, 1968-1969 (Folder 15: 14)
  - Wake Forest College, 1963 (Folder 15: 15)
  - War Control Planners, Inc., 1971 (Folder 15: 16)
  - Warbasse, James Peter, 1956 (Folder 15: 17)
  - Ward, F. Champion, 1969 (Folder 15: 18)
  - Washington Foreign Language Program newsletter, 1970 (Folder 15: 19)
  - Washington State University, undated (Folder 15: 20)
  - Weisblat, A. M., undated (Folder 15: 21)
  - Weitz, Charles B., 1969 (Folder 15: 22)
  - Wehrle, Edmund S., 1966 (Folder 15: 23)
  - Wells, Herman B., 1965 (Folder 15: 24)
  - Western Association of Africanists, 1970 (Folder 15: 25)
  - Western College for Women, 1963-1966 (Folder 15: 26)
  - Western Michigan University, 1963-1966 (Folder 15: 27)
  - Western Reserve University, 1965 (Folder 15: 28)
  - White House Conference on Education, 1965 (Folder 15: 29)
  - WICHIE (Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education), undated (Folder 15: 30)
  - Williams College, 1966 (Folder 15: 31)
  - Wilson, Dwight, 1972 (Folder 15: 32)
  - Wilton Park, 1967 (Folder 15: 33)
  - Wind and Chaff (University Chrisian Movement), 1967 (Folder 15: 34)
  - Wisconson, University of, 1967 (Folder 15: 35)
  - Wood, Arthur, 1964 (Folder 15: 36)
  - Woodward, Vann, undated (Folder 15: 37)
  - World Conference on Education for Mankind, Chicago, 1968 April 6-11 (Folder 15: 38)
  - World War I. American Historical Association (AHA) meeting on "Minority Opposition to World War I,", 1968 December (Folder 15: 38)
  - Peace Act Advisory Council, 1969-1970 (Folder 16: 1-3)
  - Peace Corps, Turkey, 1965 (Folder 16: 4-5)
  - Peace vigil, 1970 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Pendle Hill, 1962-1970 (Folder 16: 7)
  - Pennsylvania State University, 1971 (Folder 16: 8)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1964 (Folder 16: 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1965-1979 (Folder 17: 1-5)
  - Phi Kappa Phi, 1968-1973 (Folder 17: 6)
  - Philanthropy, 1971 (Folder 17: 7)
  - Phillips, Claude S., Jr., 1966 (Folder 17: 8)
  - Pinebrook Experiment, 1964 (Folder 17: 9)
  - Pirages, Dennis C. "Modernization and Political Organization: Pressures for New Decisional Models in Socialist Society,", 1968 (Folder 17: 10)
  - Polk, William R., 1969 (Folder 17: 11)
  - Polycultural education, 1963 (Folder 17: 12)
  - Pomona College, Claremont, 1963 (Folder 18: 1)
  - Population, 1965-1971 (Folder 18: 2)
  - Portuguese in Connecticut (Folder 18: 3)
    Empty file
  - Price, Derek, 1964-1971 (Folder 18: 4)
  - Princeton University (Folder 18)
    - Conference on Foreign Languages and Area Studies in the United States, 1965 (Folder 18: 5)
    - Conference on psychology, 1973 (Folder 18: 6)
    - Middle East Institute, 1948-1970 (Folder 18: 7)
  - Program statement, 1967 (Folder 18: 8)
  - Quaker United Nations program, 1965-1970 (Folder 18: 9)
  - Race, 1972 (Folder 18: 10)
  - Racism, 1972 (Folder 18: 11)
  - Regional Council for International Education, 1963-1964 (Folder 18: 12)
  - Radcliffe Institute, 1969 (Folder 19: 1)
  - Randolphe-Macon College, 1964 (Folder 19: 2)
  - Reading, 1959-1963 (Folder 19: 3)
  - Readers Digest, 1971-1972 (Folder 19: 4)
  - Realities, undated (Folder 19: 5)
  - Regional associations, 1966 (Folder 19: 6)
  - Religious articles, 1968-1969 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Religion and international affairs, 1968-1969 (Folder 19: 8)
  - Wood, Richard H., 1967 (Folder 19: 9)
  - Woodrow Wilson, 1965-1970 (Folder 19: 10)
  - Woodrow Wilson Fellowship newsletter, 1968-1972 (Folder 19: 11)
  - World Bank, 1964 (Folder 19: 12)
  - World Christian Education, 1966-1967 (Folder 19: 13)
  - World College Project, undated (Folder 19: 14)
  - World Law Fund, 1968-1972 (Folder 19: 15)
  - World University Service, 1965-1968 (Folder 19: 16)
  - World University Service India, 1964 (Folder 19: 17)
  - Yale University--Southeast Asian language studies, 1961-1972 (Folder 19: 18)
  - Arabic language, 1977 (Folder 19: 19)
  - Coombs, Philip H., 1963 (Folder 19: 20)
  - Debrezcenzi, Geza, 1977-1979 (Folder 19: 21)
  - University of Connecticut (Folder 19)
    - History Department--Search Committee, 1969 (Folder 19: 22)
    - History 342, 1971 (Folder 19: 23)
  - Statistics of Higher Education in Iran, 1975 (Folder 19: 24)
  - Education conference, Turkey, 1976 (Folder 19: 25)
- University of Connecticut file (Folder 20-21)
  - Undergraduate International Studies Mobile Outreach program at Tunxis Community College, Connecticut, 1980 (Folder 20)
    Includes two compact cassette tapes
  - World Citizen Forum newsletter, 1980 (Folder 21: 1)
  - U.S. Office of Education materials, 1980 (Folder 21: 2)
  - World Education Project, 1977-1980 (Folder 21: 3-4)
  - American Universities Field Staff (AUFS), 1979 (Folder 21: 5)
  - Office for International Education and Development (OIED), 1980 (Folder 21: 6-7)
  - Conferences and higher education in Turkey, 1982-1983 (Folder 22:)
    Includes research materials of Howard A. Reed for his writings on Turkey
  - University of Connecticut file (Folder 23:)
    - Office for International Education and Development (OIED) files, 1980-1983 (Folder 23)
      Relates mostly to education in Turkey
- Subject file (Folder 24-27)
  - Nason Committee on college and world affairs, 1965 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Nason file, 1964 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Nasson College, 1964 (Folder 24: 3)
  - National Academy of Science, 1966 (Folder 24: 4)
  - National Association of Foreign Student Affairs (NAFSA) Pasadena, 1963-1973 (Folder 24: 5)
  - National Association of Independent Schools, 1966-1972 (Folder 24: 6)
  - National Association of Secondary Schools, 1964 (Folder 24: 7)
  - National Council of Churches, 1968 (Folder 24: 8)
  - National Council for Foreign Area Materials, 1967 (Folder 24: 9)
  - National Defense Education Act (NDEA), 1961-1972 (Folder 25: 1-2)
  - National Education Association (NEA), 1964-1969 (Folder 25: 3)
  - National Educational Television, 1964 (Folder 25: 4)
  - National Foreign Policy Conference for Non-Governmental Organizations, 1966 March (Folder 25: 5)
  - National Foundation on the Arts and the Humanities, undated (Folder 25: 6)
  - National Science Foundation, 1969 (Folder 25: 7)
  - National Service, 1965-1966 (Folder 25: 8)
  - Navigation B-40, 1939; 1969 (Folder 25: 9)
  - Negro education, 1965 (Folder 25: 10)
  - Negro education, 1965 (Folder 25: 11)
  - New College, Sarasota, 1965 (Folder 25: 12)
  - New Directions Educational Fund, undated (Folder 25: 13)
  - New England Center for Continuing Education, 1968 (Folder 25: 14)
  - New Experimental College, 1965 (Folder 26: 1)
  - New Jersey Educational Association, 1964 (Folder 26: 2)
  - New World Foundation, undated (Folder 26: 3)
  - New York University, 1966 (Folder 26: 4)
  - Newsletters (miscellaneous), 1964; 1973 (Folder 26: 5)
  - Nieuwenhuijze, Christoffel Anthonie Olivier Van, 1968 (Folder 26: 6)
  - Nigeria--Education and World Affairs article, 1967 (Folder 26: 7)
  - North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools Foreign Relations Project, 1964-1969 (Folder 26: 8)
  - Northeastern University, 1964 (Folder 26: 9)
  - Oberlin College, 1970 (Folder 26: 10)
  - Oberling, Pierre, 1972 (Folder 26: 11)
    Essay on Reza Shah of Iran
  - Occidental College, 1963-1966 (Folder 26: 12)
    Relates in part to education in Turkey
  - Ohio, 1964 (Folder 26: 13)
  - Ohio University, 1964 (Folder 26: 14)
  - Operation Smithsonian, 1962-1965 (Folder 26: 15)
  - Oregon, 1965 (Folder 26: 16)
  - Oregon State Colleges Regional Conference, 1965-1966 (Folder 26: 17)
  - Oregon State University, undated (Folder 26: 18)
  - Overseas, 1964-1965 (Folder 27: 1)
  - Overseas aid, 1971-1972 (Folder 27: 2)
  - Pace, Carlo, 1972 (Folder 27: 3)
  - Pacem in Terris (Peace on Earth), 1965 (Folder 27: 4)
  - Pacific School of Religion, undated (Folder 27: 5)
  - Parsons College, 1966 (Folder 27: 6)
  - Presidential Commission (Rand Corporation), 1978-1979 (Folder 27: 7-8)